Gustav Rehberger
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Gustav Rehberger papers
1924-2004
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Rehberger, Gustav
4.0 linear feet
The Gustav Rehberger papers measure 4 linear feet and date from 1924 to 2004. Rehberger's career as an illustrator, painter, educator, and performance artist is documented by correspondence, scrapbooks, printed material, photographs, and sound and video recordings.
Provenance
The Gustav Rehberger papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2004 by his widow, Pamela Demme.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Gustav Rehberger (1910-1995) was an illustrator, designer, painter, educator, and performance artist in New York City.
The Rehberger family emigrated from Austria to Chicago in 1923. At age 14, Rehberger began studying at the Art Institute of Chicago on a scholarship that continued for three years. While still a teenager, he also was enrolled in The Art Instruction Schools, Minneapolis. After declining two college scholarships, he worked as a graphic designer and illustrator to help support his family during the Depression. Fom 1929-1942, he was Art Director at Reuben H. Donnelly Corporation in Chicago, publishers of telephone directories.
During World War II, the Wartime Committee of the Society of Typographic Artists commissioned Rehberger to paint two murals for the interior of Chicago's Union Station (1942). He moved to New York City in 1943 and soon enlisted in the U.S. Army Air Forces. While in the service, Rehberger was assigned to the Illustrations and Format Branch where he created visual training aids.
After the war, Rehberger's illustrations appeared in the national advertising campaigns of Celanese Chemicals, Philip Morris and Sheraton Hotels; were featured in major newspaper and magazines such as Chicago Daily Tribune, The New York Times, and Esquire; and in various Christian publications.
In order to focus on painting, in 1969 Rehberger ceased commercial work. From 1972-1993 he taught drawing, anatomy, and composition at the Art Students League of New York. He also became interested in performance art. Evolving out of his classroom drawing demonstrations, Rehberger's performances - the act of painting and drawing before a live audience - soon moved to formal performance spaces and often were accompanied by recorded music.
Throughout his career, Rehberger participated in numerous group shows and was the recipient of many awards and prizes. He also had a number of solo exhibitions, among them shows at the Society of Illustrators in New York, National Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C., and National Gallery of Art in London.
Gustav Rehberger died in New York City on July 22, 1995.
Scope and Content Note
The Gustav Rehberger papers measure 4.0 linear feet and date from 1924 to 2004. His career as an illustrator, painter, educator, and performance artist is documented by correspondence, scrapbooks, printed material, photographs, and sound and video recordings.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, circa 2003 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1938-2003 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 3: Scrapbooks, 1924-2004; Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1937-1972; Boxes 2, 6; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 5: Artwork, 1927-1942 (Boxes 2, 6; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, 1927-1995 (Boxes 2-3, 6; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Sound and Video Recordings, 1972-1995 (Boxes 4-5; 0.5 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Educators--New York (State)--New York; Illustrators--New York (State)--New York; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Performance artists--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sound recordings; Video recordings
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Materials, circa 2003, Series 1:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  Rehberger's curriculum vitae and chronology were prepared and added by the family.
  - Curriculum Vitae and Chronology, circa 2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1938-2003, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
  Correspondence is of a professional nature and is mainly with graphic designers and publishers.
  Although the correspondence from "Book I" and "Book II" has been removed from the binders, original order has been retained. Additional corresponence is found in the scrapbooks (series 3).
  - Book I, 1938-2001, undated, (1 volume, removed from binder) (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Book II, 1943-2003, undated, (1 volume, removed from binder) (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - Gustav Rehberger v. Reader's Digest Association, Inc., 1990-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Scrapbooks, 1924-2004, Series 3:; (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
  Scrapbooks are composed mostly of items reproducing illustrations by Rehberger.
  Although volumes were removed from their binders, the original order remains.
  - Scrapbook I, 1924-2004, undated, (1 volume, removed from binder) (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - Scrapbook II, 1975-2003, undated, (1 volume, removed from binder) (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
  - The Art Students League of New York, 1972-1996, (1 volume, removed from binder) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gallery Exhibition Guest Books, 1964-1977, (1 volume, removed from binder) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Military, 1943-1945, (2 volumes removed from binders) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Movie Illustrations, 1953-1992, (1 volume, removed from binder) (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
- Printed Material, 1937-1972, Series 4:; (Boxes 2, 6; 0.6 linear feet)
  Books, both illustrated by Rehberger, are: The Gospel Story of Jesus by Benjamin Bedenbaugh and Luther by Robert H. Fischer.
  - Everywoman's Magazine, 1955-1957, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Illustrations, Miscellaneous, 1937-1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Books, 1964-1966 (2 volumes) (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Church Publications, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Reproductions of Miscellaneous Artwork (1980s), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Printed Material, 1936-1992 (Box 6)
    27 Chicago Designers
    Calendars
    Esquire
    Sheraton Hotels
    World War II, Union Station, Chicago
  - Oversized Printed Material, 1962-1964, undated (Folder OV 7)
    Celanese Chemicals
    New York Times and Chicago Daily Tribune
- Artwork, 1927-1942, Series 5:; (Boxes 2, 6; 0.6 linear feet)
  Of particular interest are maquette drawings of Rehberger's murals for Chicago's Union Station (1942).
  - Schoolwork Assignments, 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbooks, undated, (9 volumes) (Box 2, Folder 8-11)
  - Index Cards of Sketches, undated (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
  - Oversized Artwork, Paintings, 1942 (Box 6)
- Photographs, 1927-1995, Series 6:; (Boxes, 2-3, 6; 1.2 linear feet)
  Photographs are of Rehberger, artwork, lectures, and performances.
  - Photographs (Box 2)
    - Rehberger (1920s-1990s), undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Rehberger with Artwork (1950s-1990s), 1991-1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
    - Art Students League Lectures, Art and Music Performance, 1972-1993 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Illustrations, Miscellaneous (1949-1989), undated (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Artwork and Classroom Demonstratoins (1960s-1993), undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Artwork, Miscellaneous (1927-1992), undated, (oversized material housed in Box 6) (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
  - Transparencies (Box 3)
    - Illustrations (1943-1969) undated, (6 folders) (Box 3, Folder 7-12)
    - Artwork (1949-1993), undated (Box 3, Folder 13-22)
    - Slides (Box 3)
    - Artwork and Classroom Demonstrations (1972-1995), undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Artwork, Miscellaneous (1960s-1991) (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
- Sound and Video Recordings, 1972-1995, Series 7:; (Boxes 4-5; 0.5 linear feet)
  Five sound cassettes and 11 videocassettes record interviews with Rehberger, lectures, his memorial service, demonstrations and performances.
  - Interviews, Lectures, and Memorial Service, 1986-1995, (5 sound cassettes) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Pastel Society Demonstratons, Two Horses, 1990, (2 videocassettes: VHS) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Documentary Footage, 1972, 1990, (2 videocassettes: VHS) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Performances, 1982-1983, undated, (3 videocassettes: VHS) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Art Students League Lectures, 1987, 1990, undated, (4 videocassettes: VHS) (Box 5, Folder 1-2)